<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Societies for Reformation of Manners in Dublin, April the 11th, 1699 by Alex. Sinclare ; published at the desire of the said societies.</title>
            <author>Sinclare, Alex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60280</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3852</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33745</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13553532</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13553532</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60280)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1557:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Societies for Reformation of Manners in Dublin, April the 11th, 1699 by Alex. Sinclare ; published at the desire of the said societies.</title>
                  <author>Sinclare, Alex.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Brocas ... for John Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 2nd, XXXIV, 32 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of Manners</hi> IN DUBLIN, <hi>April</hi> the 11th, 1699. By <hi>ALEX. SINCLARE.</hi> Publiſhed at the Deſire of the ſaid Societies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>DUBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Brocas</hi> in <hi>School-Houſe-Lane,</hi> near <hi>High-Street,</hi> for <hi>John Bentley</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Nicholas-Street,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Tholſel,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:2"/>
            <head>TO THE SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of Manners.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THAT Glorious Work which you have the Honour to be imployed in; hath afforded abundant Matter for your Great and Noble Attempts; and alſo a very large and pleaſing Subject for the many Excellent Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that have been Preach'd and Publiſh'd to inſtruct and quicken you therein.</p>
            <p>But this Field (how fruitful ſoever it was) hath been reapt down by ſo many more Skilful Labourers, that I have been left, with the <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> Damſel, only to glean among their Sheaves; but hope for the Charity of <hi>Boaz,</hi> that if I gather ſome handfuls they have let fall, I ſhall not be reproach'd.</p>
            <p>But I will not make any further Apologies (how needful ſoever they may be) for my defects in this Performance; for it is enough, that what I have done was in compliance with your Deſires, whom I eſteem very highly for your Works ſake; and in Obedience to their united Requeſts, to whoſe Spirits mine ought to be ſubject: and that by overcoming the Reluctancy I had to expoſe my Weakneſs in this manner; I give the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Teſtimony of my fervent, if not prudent, Zeal for the Work you are engaged in.</p>
            <p>A Work that was the Deſire of former Ages, is the Glory of this; and may leave a Bleſſing for thoſe to come: which the Covenant of God, the God of your Fathers, doth oblige you to be active in: which hath derived many Signal Bleſſings upon us already. And that it is the great Duty and Honour of the Zealous Inhabitants of our <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and how far it may determine our future Condition; and that our Hopes and Fears depend upon the Succeſs of it, I have endeavoured to ſhow, in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:3"/>
            <p>You are encouraged, by the Preſence and Promiſes of God, whoſe Cauſe it is, and who hath bleſt you with wonderful Succeſs: And alſo by the excellent Zeal of his Vicegerent, our great <hi>Joſiah,</hi> who hath given Life and Vigour to it: May he be alſo as <hi>David</hi> (as he reſembles him in many other things) to prepare abundant Materials, to build a moſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and laſting Temple for Generations to come. Nay, may he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> not only to lay the Foundation, but alſo to hold the Plummet in his hand till he hath finiſhed it, and brought forth the head Stone thereof. And may he be as Succeſsful to vanquiſh the Devil's Kingdom at home, by a more Glorious Conqueſt; as he hath been to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Enemies abroad to an Honourable Peace. You, and ſuch as you, are his Worthies and Armies, upon whom he muſt rely in this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare againſt the Powers of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Our Elders alſo have ſtrengthened your Hands, by their ready Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, to Enact many good and neceſſary Laws that you are to aſſist in the Execution of: Our Governours and Judges, our Magiſtrates and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable Perſons, both in Church and State, do give their help and countenance to it. So that many great Names of Majeſty and Honour, Excellency and Juſtice; Grace and Authority, are all on your ſide: and many more of all ranks and ſorts of Perſons, do now approve your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Deſigns, and are daily coming over to you. And ſhall not all this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite your Zeal, quicken your Diligence, and encourage your Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and reproach them that are yet backward to joyn with you, and aſſist in ſuch an Honourable, and Succeſsful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking.</p>
            <p>And it's no ſmall Encouragement, that ſo many of different Perſwaſions in other matters, do ſo heartily conſpire together to carry on this happy Work, wherein we are all agreed; who do alſo provoke one another to a generous Emulation of promoting the great Deſigns of our common Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: not to a ſpiteful Envy, that hath been the Curſe and Character of the unhappy times that are paſt: and may they be for ever paſt. And may the Bleſſed God continue to protect and honour your Perſons, direct all your Counſels, and proſper your Zealous Endeavours in this, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Work: and may he cauſe the Dawnings of this Bleſſed Day to ſhine more and more, till all the promiſer Mercies to his Church and People in this World have their Accompliſhment; and bring us to that perfect State where there ſhall be no need of a Reformation: Theſe are, and ſhall be, the earneſt Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Friend, and Faithful Servant in the Goſpel,</hi> Alex. Sinclare.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100231:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the <hi>Societies for Reformation,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Chron.</hi> Ch. <hi>34. latter part of</hi> verſ. <hi>32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did according to the Covenant of God, the God of their Fathers.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Text, <hi>I have choſen,</hi> ſeems Calculated for this Meridian; and evidently appears to be ſuitable to the preſent Occaſion: For it's an everlaſting Record; to the great <hi>Honour</hi> of the illuſtrious Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> for their <hi>active Zeal,</hi> in the moſt Glorious Reformation, that was ever known in the Kingdom of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi> This Bleſſed Work had its firſt Riſe and Spring in the tender Heart of that great Reformer,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.19.27.</note> the <hi>incomparable</hi> Joſiah; who carried it on to ſuch a <hi>perfection;</hi> That, after a large deſcription of its <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> Progreſs; it's ſaid,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.1.24.</note> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 23.25. That, <hi>Like unto him there was no King before him, that turned to the Lord with all his Heart, and with all his Soul, and with all his Might, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all the Law of</hi> Moſes; <hi>neither after him Aroſe there any like him.</hi> He called the <hi>Elders</hi> together, and cauſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100231:4"/>all the <hi>People</hi> to enter into a Covenant, to turn unto the Lord: But theſe <hi>Renown'd</hi> inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem, Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalized</hi> themſelves beyond all others; by their ready <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance,</hi> and needful Aſſiſtance; for they <hi>Did according to the Covenant of God, the God of their Fathers.</hi> And that this <hi>High</hi> Commendation of them may be well underſtood and fitly applied; I ſhall briefly explain theſe three Things in it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Who theſe <hi>Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>were.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. What is <hi>the Covenant of God, the God of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>III. How they <hi>did according to it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The firſt of theſe will be eaſily known; if you conſider, That <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was the Metropolis, or chief City, of the Kingdom of <hi>Judah;</hi> and that theſe Inhabitants of it are diſtinguiſhed, not only from them that <hi>were preſent in</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem <hi>and</hi> Benjamin; and them that <hi>pertained to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael, mentioned in the Context before and after: But alſo from the <hi>Elders</hi> ſpoken of,<note place="margin">Ab eo decreta &amp; judicia exibant in omnem <hi>Iſraelem.</hi> Dr. <hi>Light. Vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 609.</note> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. who were the <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> or <hi>Members</hi> of the great <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> the Supreme Council, and Court of Judicature, not unlike to our Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments. <hi>Theſe</hi> the King gathered together, to adviſe about the neceſſary and <hi>arduous Matters</hi> of the Kingdom, who ſpeedily performed their Parts: And therefore <hi>theſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> are chiefly to be underſtood of <hi>private Perſons</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in this City; and ſuch only I expect my <hi>Hearers</hi> to be, and therefore ſhall not be ſolicitous to extend the Words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The <hi>Covenant of God,</hi> &amp;c. is the Divine Law, written in the Books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> with their <hi>ſolemnly declared Conſent;</hi> which gives it the proper Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a <hi>Covenant. This</hi> Book was <hi>found</hi> by <hi>Hilkiah</hi> the High-Prieſt in the Temple, and <hi>brought</hi> to the King, who read it in the <hi>Ears</hi> of the People, both great and ſmall, that were met together in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of the Lord; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>ſolemnly engaged himſelf</hi> to walk after the Lord, to keep
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100231:4"/>his Commandments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he <hi>cauſed them</hi> alſo to declare and give <hi>their</hi> Conſent, and is <hi>therefore</hi> called the <hi>Book of the Covenant,</hi> v. 30. <hi>And in the Text, the Covenant of God, the God of their Fathers;</hi> becauſe it contains the <hi>Terms</hi> of that Covenant which God made with their Fathers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 24.7.8.</note> and the <hi>manner</hi> of its ſolemn Ratification; when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkled the <hi>Blood</hi> upon the Altar, and the People, who declared their Conſent, by ſaying, <hi>All that the Lord hath ſaid, we will do, and be Obedient,</hi> Ex. 24.7. And now it may be <hi>well</hi> ſuppoſed, that they <hi>Renewed</hi> this Covenant, and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly</hi> engaged themſelves to perform <hi>all the words of it;</hi> as its here ſaid, They <hi>did according to the Covenant of God, the God of their Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They are chiefly commended here, for <hi>doing</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Covenant; which ſignifies their <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>active</hi> diligence, by which they <hi>excell'd</hi> all others: For whereas the reſt were rather <hi>paſſive</hi> to ſuffer the Reformation to be carried on, which they <hi>could</hi> not hinder, and <hi>durſt</hi> not oppoſe; as its ſaid, the King <hi>cauſed them</hi> by conſtraint, <hi>to ſtand,</hi> or give their Conſent, <hi>to the Covenant,</hi> and that he <hi>made,</hi> or compelled them, by ſome neceſſary force upon their backward inclinations, <hi>to ſerve, even to ſerve the Lord their God:</hi> But the more <hi>Noble</hi> inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered themſelves <hi>willingly</hi> and were <hi>active;</hi> both to Reform themſelves, and to <hi>aſſiſt</hi> all they could to Reform others. That they complied with the Covenant, and were <hi>active</hi> to Reform themſelves, is plainly ſignified by this Expreſſion. And that it further implies their <hi>neceſſary</hi> Aſſiſtance to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form others alſo, will evidently appear, if we conſider theſe two things.</p>
            <p>1. That this <hi>Glorious Reformer</hi> put away all the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that were <hi>ſpied in the Land of</hi> Judah, <hi>and in Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King</hi> 23.24.</note> and by a <hi>juſt</hi> execution of the Law, <hi>reclaimed</hi> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that were unwilling, and compell'd them <hi>to ſerve the Lord;</hi> which he could not do by himſelf alone, but ſtood in need of <hi>Informers</hi> to aſſiſt him; and we Read of <hi>none</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100231:5"/>others that <hi>did</hi> ſo, but theſe <hi>Honored</hi> Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. That it was a <hi>part</hi> of the Covenant; for the Divine Law commanded it; That <hi>all the People</hi> ſhould aſſiſt in the Puniſhment of notorious Offenders, that could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be <hi>Reclaimed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> And we have <hi>no</hi> cauſe to doubt; that the Zealous Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did according to this part of the Covenant of God. And their <hi>generous</hi> aſſiſtance was Crowned with <hi>Glorious</hi> Succeſs, to ſpread the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in an <hi>eminent</hi> manner thro' the whole Kingdom; and a ſpecial <hi>Mark</hi> of the Divine Favour, and the <hi>Honour</hi> that comes from God, is here fix't upon theſe <hi>Renown'd</hi> inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And now from all that hath been ſaid, doth clearly ariſe this.</p>
            <p>Doct. 1.<note place="margin" type="runSum">DoctriN. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That it's a ſingular advantage to the Publick Work of Reformation, and will redound to the great Honour of the Inhabitants of the chief City of a Kingdom, when they are vigorouſly engaged in it, to Reform themſelves, and all others as they have Opportunity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Proſecution of this Truth, I ſhall only propoſe to your Conſideration theſe two Propoſitions that are implied, and inforce them with two Arguments that are expreſſly contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That when a <hi>Publick Reformation</hi> is happily begun by the Supreme Powers, and carried on by the juſt Execution of neceſſary Laws in that Caſe made and provided: All Perſons ſhould not only ſubmit to them, and be active to Reform themſelves, but alſo aſſiſt all they can in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Stations and Capacities to Reclaim others.</p>
            <p>For to <hi>reſiſt</hi> and ſeek to be Revenged on them, who are ready to perform ſuch a kind and needful Office, and ſo <hi>to render Evil for Good;</hi> is <hi>helliſh Madneſs,</hi> and to Act like Devils incarnate;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jo.</hi> 8.44.</note> for as Chriſt ſays of ſuch: <hi>They are of their Father the Devil, and the Luſts of their Father they will do, who was a Murderer from the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to be only <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and tamely ſuffer themſelves to be Reclaimed, or patiently to bear the juſt Puniſhment of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100231:5"/>their Miſcarriages; is no better than <hi>brutiſh Subjection,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32.9.</note> and to act like <hi>the Horſe or Mule that muſt be held in with Bitt and Bridle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, To be <hi>active</hi> only to comply with the Precepts of the Law, and Reform themſelves, is but humane Prudence, and to acquit themſelves meerly as Men, that are capable of Moral Government.</p>
            <p>But to give a good Example by their own cheerful Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and vigorouſly endeavour to Reform others alſo; is a Noble act of that excellent grace of <hi>Charity,</hi> which the Chriſtian Religion doth indiſpenſibly require, by which they imitate God himſelf, and act like his Children.</p>
            <p>And, That this is the neceſſary Duty, not only of <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates</hi> in Authority, who muſt not <hi>bear the Sword in vain;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.4.</note> but alſo of private Perſons as they have Opportunity and Abilities, in their Places and Stations, to be aiding and aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by their faithful Informations, wiſe Counſels, ſocial Combinations, vigorous Proſecutions, liberal Contributions, and all other lawful and neceſſary means to Reform a vitious Age. This hath been ſo fully Explained, Proved, Preſs't and Vindicated, in thoſe excellent Diſcourſes that have been Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh't on this Occaſion, That I ſhall only refer you to them, and proceed to another Propoſition implied here.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Inhabitants of the chief City of a Kingdom, ſhould be the moſt forward and active to engage themſelves in this Work;</hi> to be the firſt and moſt illuſtrious inſtances of ſincere Obedience to the Laws, by their own perſonal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; and alſo to aſſiſt, with their utmoſt diligence, in the juſt Execution of them upon Notorious Offenders, that their fellow Citizens being firſt Reclaimed; the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be likewiſe Reformed.</p>
            <p>This may well be expected from them, who ought to be firſt and beſt acquainted with the Laws to be put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as they would be thought, and are generally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed to be Men of better Parts, and higher Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to have greater Abilities, and more Advantages; to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100231:6"/>excel others in Wiſdom, Riches, Intereſt and Conduct; and to be intruſted with many excellent Talents, that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify them to be uſeful Inſtruments in ſuch a Work: So they muſt give an awful and ſtrict <hi>Account,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.19. <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.48.</note> how they have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them for the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and in the ſervice of their Generation according to the Opportunities put into their Hands.</p>
            <p>But there are two Arguments expreſſly contained in the Doctrine, that are ſufficient to confirm and enforce this which I will briefly mention, and is all that I ſhall ſay upon it.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>That their Zealous Endeavours will exceedingly advance the Work thro' the Nation. And</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>They will greatly inhance their own Glory.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. It's a <hi>ſingular advantage to the Publick Work of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> to make it ſpread thro' the whole Kingdom, when the Inhabitants of the chief City are vigorouſly engaged in it; for the Glorious Luſtre of their excellent Example, will provoke many to imitate them; and the powerful influences of their ſucceſsful Attempts be quickly diſperſed thro' all the Country: For as the Blood circulating thro' the Heart, receives a freſh Vigour and Tincture, which it conveys to all parts to repair the Health and Strength of the whole; ſo the Trade and Treaſure of a Nation doth uſually circulate thro' the chief City, and brings there a continual concourſe of the moſt <hi>active</hi> people from all Parts, who receiving the impreſſions of your Zealous Diligence to Reform them; will carry them back and communicate them to others, as the moſt profitable part of their Traffick. And as plentiful Streams derive their noxious or wholſome Vertues from their Springs, and carry them to all places where they flow; ſo the Fountains of Virtue and Vice are uſually found in the chief Cities of a Kingdom, and thence diſperſe themſelves thro' the whole Land;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.15. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 2.3.</note> for both <hi>Profaneſs and the Word of the Lord went forth from</hi> Jeruſalem. We have obſerved by ſad experience, how the Contagion of that Wickedneſs which began and reigned in our chief Cities, did quickly ſpread
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100231:6"/>thro' the whole Nation; and why may not the influence of your Virtue; when this <hi>Metropolis</hi> is Reformed, prevail as much, and ſpread as far? Let us cleanſe the Fountains, and the Streams will run clear. Surely the good and wiſe King <hi>Joſiah</hi> took this Courſe; when he firſt cauſed them that were preſent in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſtand to the Covenant, and took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all the abominations that were Spied there; and then put away the like abominations, out of all <hi>the Countries that pertained to the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and made them to ſerve the Lord.</hi> And now, if ever we expect a general Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this Kingdom, it muſt begin and receive its ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful Vigour by your Zealous endeavours in this <hi>City.</hi> Be <hi>ſtrong therefore all ye People,</hi> and be Active, ye Inhabitants of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ye may have the Honour of being the happy Reformers, not only of one City, but alſo of a whole Nation. This brings me to the ſecond Argument to Encourage and Quicken your Diligence, which is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That it will redound to your own immortal Glory.</hi> The Work it ſelf is Honourable, to Vindicate the Glory of the Blaſphemed Name of <hi>God,</hi> and the Honour of his broken Laws and deſpiſed Government; to Conquer the <hi>Devils</hi> Kingdom, and vanquiſh all the ruleing Powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; to reſtrain <hi>Lewd</hi> and <hi>Prophane</hi> Sinners from their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Courſes, and reſcue them, as far as you can, from their everlaſting Perdition; to repair the almoſt ſunk Credit of our Holy Profeſſion, and reſtore Religion to its Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power and Purity; to prevent, if poſſible, the direful Executions of impending Judgments, and derive many laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bleſſings upon the Nation: This is the Work you are engaged in; theſe and ſuch like are the Glorious Effects and Tendencies of it; which are greater than all the Victories of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who having Conquered the World, could not Reform one Perſon; No, <hi>not himſelf.</hi> And all the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Titles of the moſt Renown'd <hi>Hero</hi>'s on Earth, are flat, and not to be compared with the Honourable Name of <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Reformers.</hi> 'Tis God himſelf, the Fountain of all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100231:7"/>Glory, who confers this Honour upon you, and doth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord your Names in his Book; as he did the Noble Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> where they ſhall be more durable than if they were ingraven on <hi>Braſs</hi> or <hi>Marble.</hi> You are Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable in his Account, and he will make others to Eſteem you ſo; for he hath ſet you upon High Places to be ſeen and admired by all;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 5.14.16.</note> You Act in a <hi>City ſet upon a Hill, that your Light may ſo ſhine before Men, that they ſeeing your good works, may Glorify your Father which is in Heaven:</hi> You move in one of our higheſt Orbs; that you may diſperſe your influences farther; and if you <hi>turn many to Righteouſneſs,</hi> ſhall be Tranſlated much higher,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3.</note> to <hi>ſhine as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> This Argument hath been ſo excellently Diſcourſed and well improved already, to excite your Zealous Diligence; that I will not further inſiſt upon it.<note place="margin">Vid. Mr. <hi>Emlins</hi> Reform. Sermon.</note> And verily, I find it ſo hard to ſay any thing upon this Subject, that hath not been much better expreſſed by others; that I will leave this Doctrine as it is, with what I have ſaid upon it; and before I come to the Application, will ſeek for, and raiſe another, from two principal Circumſtances of the Text, which are the <hi>antecedent Occaſion,</hi> and <hi>conſequent iſſue</hi> of this Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were ſo Active in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>antecedent Occaſion of it, was their danger of the Wrath of God,</hi> which was ſo expreſſly threatned againſt them, that it's ſpoken of <hi>v.</hi> 21. as already <hi>poured</hi> out upon them. This broke the tender Heart of good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that <hi>he Rent his Cloaths, and humbled himſelf before God,</hi> with penitential <hi>Tears;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 27, 28.</note> and was therefore aſſured by a Meſſage from the Lord; That his <hi>eyes ſhould not ſee all the Evil that he would bring upon that Place, and the Inhabitants of it.</hi> But knowing that he muſt uſe the means, and that none was more neceſſary than a thoro' Reformation; he applied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf effectually to it. He gathers the Elders, and calls the People together; cauſed them to enter into a ſolemn Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and made them to put away their Abominations and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100231:7"/>ſerve the Lord, that the Judgments threatned againſt them might be averted; and upon this Occaſion, the Zealous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were more active than others, to do according to the Covenant, and would have been happily delivered, if they had been as ſincere and conſtant in it as their King was.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Behold the conſequent iſſue of all this; that it was not ſufficient to appeaſe the incenſed Wrath of a provoked God, and to free them wholly from the dreadful effects of it: For after a large Deſcription of the great ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this Glorious Reformation, in 2 <hi>Kings ch.</hi> 23. from the beginning to <hi>v.</hi> 25. it immediately follows in <hi>v.</hi> 26. That <hi>notwithſtanding the Lord turned not from the fierceneſs of his great Wrath, wherewith his Anger was kindled againſt</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, <hi>becauſe of all the provocations, that</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked him withal.</hi> And the event was anſwerable to this terrible Denunciation; when their Land was laid utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, their City and Temple wholly Deſtroyed, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of their people cruelly Slain; and the reſt carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a miſerable Captivity, and kept there for a long and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious 70 Years: So that hence you may Obſerve,</p>
            <p>2d Doct. <hi>That an external Reformation begun in the chief City, and carried on with great ſucceſs thro' the Kingdom; is the neceſſary means to prevent, and may ſometimes effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally delay: But it is not always ſufficient wholly to avert the Execution of impending Judgments from a ſinful Nation.</hi> In this Doctrine are only theſe two Parts, that I will take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That ſuch a Reformation is the neceſſary means to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert impending Judgments, and may effectually delay the Execution of them for ſometime. This the tender hearted <hi>Joſiah,</hi> and Zealous Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of; and alſo ſucceſsful, by their Bleſſed Endeavours, to deliver themſelves and the Nation from the deſtructive Miſeries they had deſerv'd, during his good Reign, and four bad Kings that ſucceeded him. In which time, the Lord
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100231:8"/>waited to be gracious to them, rewarded their preſent At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, and made a further Tryal of their ſincerity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in this Reformation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6.</note> But, <hi>becauſe they deſpiſed the Riches of his goodneſs and forbearance, and long ſufiering that ſhould have led them to Repentance: After their Hardneſs and impenitent Hearts, they Treaſured up unto themſelves Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath, and Revelation of the Righteous Judgment of God, who rendered to them at laſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Deeds:</hi> Therefore,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such an external Reformation, is not always ſufficient to deliver a ſinful Nation from the Calamities which they have long provoked a Jealous God to threaten againſt them: For there may be ſuch Defects in a Reformation of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that will render it altogether ineffectual to procure their Pardon, and freedom from his righteous Judgments: So that I will next enquire what were the <hi>fatal Defects</hi> of this great Reformation, and the Cauſes of their conſequent Miſeries, notwithſtanding all that was done to eſcape them; and will only mention theſe two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>They turned not to the Lord with their whole Heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.6, 10.</note> but feignedly:</hi> as they are reproved by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> when he Propheſied in the days of <hi>Joſiah</hi> the King. And there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears too much Evidence for ſuch a Charge in the Hiſtory of his Reformation.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.25.</note> For tho' the <hi>upright</hi> Joſiah <hi>turned to the Lord with all his Heart, and with all his Soul, and with all his Might:</hi> Yet the generality of the People had no Heart to the Work, but were forced to it, and went no farther than the Beaſt:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.32, 33.</note> for it's ſaid, that he cauſed them to ſtand to the Covenant, and made them to ſerve, even to ſerve the Lord;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which they had no mind to do, if they had not been compelled to it. For what is ſaid, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 23.3. That they did it with all <hi>their</hi> Heart. and all <hi>their</hi> Soul, ſeems to be a defect in our Tranſlation; for there is no ſuch Relative Particle in the Original,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.31. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and the Grammatical Conſtruction neceſſarily refers it to the King alone, for he is the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſpoken of in the beginning of the Sentence: And ſo it is applied to him only in <hi>v.</hi> 31 of this Chapter, where the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100231:8"/>Affix is uſed in the Singular Number, and thus Tranſlated; that <hi>the King ſtood in his Place, and made a Covenant before the Lord, to walk after the Lord, to keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Teſtimonies, and Statutes, with all his Heart, and with all his Soul.</hi> But the People were not ſincere, and no ſuch Commendation is given of them; for they ſtill loved their former Sins, tho' they left them for a while; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quickly turned to them again when the reſtraint was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off in the ſucceeding Reigns: And a <hi>Jealous God</hi> who judges according to the Affections of Mens Hearts, would not be impoſed upon by their outward temporary Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but doth charge their Sins upon them ſtill, continues his Threatnings againſt them, and at laſt executes upon them all the Judgments they deſerved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They made no Publick Confeſſion of their groſs and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied Sins,</hi> nor gave any Signs of a National Repentance for them; which the Prophet doth plainly inſinuate to be their dangerous Neglect, when he exhorts them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Only acknowledge thine Iniquity that thou haſt tranſgreſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord thy God, and haſt ſcattered thy Ways: and ye have not obey'd my Voice, ſaith the Lord.</hi> They compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Command of the King, to <hi>Reform;</hi> but neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the Calls of God, by his Prophets, to <hi>Repent.</hi> And this is alſo obſervable in the Account we have of their Reformation; that tho' the tender-hearted Joſiah <hi>rent his Cloaths, and humbled himſelf with Tears before the Lord;</hi> yet we do not read of any one more that did ſo. And tho' the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> acquitted themſelves like Men,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.27.</note> and were active to reform themſelves and others; yet moſt of them came ſhort of being <hi>Penitent Saints, and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned Sinners.</hi> They were prevailed with to forſake their Sins, but not to <hi>expoſe</hi> them by an <hi>open Acknowledgement</hi> of their Iniquities. Being over tender, it may be, of their own, and the Reputation of the former wicked Reigns, they were willing to be <hi>reformed,</hi> without any publick Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. or expreſſions of their Grief and Shame, for their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100231:9"/>aggravated Tranſgreſſions. We find afterward, in more ſucceſsful Reformations by <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.1, 3. <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.1, 3.</note> that all the People joyned with them in their <hi>Publick Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Penitential Sorrows</hi> for their Sins. And this the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſuggeſts to them as <hi>moſt</hi> neceſſary to juſtifie God in his Treatnings,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>So</hi> David <hi>thought, Pſ.</hi> 51.4.</note> and the <hi>only</hi> effectual means to turn away his Wrath from them and procure his Favour. The Guilt of Sin, or its actual Obligation to Puniſhment, doth always remain till it's removed by a Repentance ſuitable to the Nature of it: So that private Repentance may be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Pardon of ſecret Sins; but National Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons require ſome publick Acts of Repentance to vindicate the Glory of God. and prevent the Execution of National Judgments. And therefore, becauſe they did not glorifie God by a <hi>Publick Confeſſion</hi> of their Iniquities; he <hi>glorified</hi> himſelf upon them by their General Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the two fatal Defects in <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Reformation; That tho' it was <hi>ſucceſsful</hi> to <hi>delay,</hi> yet theſe made it ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to deliver them <hi>wholly</hi> from the juſt Executions of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance. And now, what remains but to make ſome <hi>Application.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 1. By ſuggeſting to you ſome cauſes of our <hi>Fears.</hi> 2. By ſhewing you the Grounds of our <hi>Hopes,</hi> concerning the Iſſue of our preſent Reformation. 3. By giving ſome <hi>Directions</hi> how you ſhould behave your ſelves, that if it be poſſible, we may eſcape the Calamities that our National Sins have deſerved. I ſhall begin with the firſt of theſe, by comparing our Condition with that of <hi>Judah;</hi> and if we ſhall find, upon inquiry, that ours is like to theirs, nay. if ours appears to be much worſe, what reaſon then ſhall we have to fear, that we are ſtill in danger of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries we deſerve? And</p>
            <p n="1">1. The chief and fundamental cauſe of our Fear is, <hi>the great Provocations we have been guilty of,</hi> which are too too like the Sins of <hi>Judah,</hi> if they do not exceed; and deſerve ſeverer Judgments than were inflicted upon them. And tho' I might run the Parallel much farther backward, yet I ſhall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100231:9"/>confine my ſelf at preſent to that which is expreſly mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.6.</note> as the reaſon why <hi>the Lord turned not from the fierceneſs of his great Wrath, wherewith his Anger was kindled againſt</hi> Judah, viz. <hi>The Provocations that</hi> Manaſſeh <hi>had provoked him withal, i. e.</hi> The groſs Iniquities that were committed in his Reign; countenanced, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluenced by his Command and Example; and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued through the much ſhorter, but as wicked Reign of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> his Succeſſor: And hath not the profligate Wickedneſs and Impiety, the horrible Profaneneſs and Lewdneſs, of the <hi>two late Reigns</hi> been equal to theirs? I have not time to mention either of them, nor to compare them both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You may do it your ſelves if you'll read 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 21 <hi>ch.</hi> and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33 <hi>ch.</hi> And conſider what hath been acted of late in theſe Kingdoms; for which God may as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely puniſh us. as he did <hi>Judah</hi> for their Sins.</p>
            <p>The 2d cauſe of our Fear. <hi>is from the Diſpenſations of Gods Patience; who hath long ſpared us, and his Patience been as oft abuſed by us:</hi> So that this may be the laſt Tryal he will take of us; and if we ſtill provoke him to anger he may reſolve to paſs by us no more. For this was the caſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> as it's repreſented by the Propheſie of <hi>Am.</hi> 7.1.8. That he firſt threatned to ſend the Graſs-hoppers to devour them; but at the Interceſſion of the Prophet, the Lord <hi>repented,</hi> and removed them. And again he <hi>called to contend by Fire; but this alſo ſhall not be, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And laſt of all he appears <hi>with a Plumb-Line,</hi> to take a ſtricter Account of them, and declares that he will not paſs by them any more. And hath not the Lord been dealing ſo with us. when he delivered us from the <hi>Spaniſh Armado</hi> that appeared as <hi>Sea-monſters</hi> ready to devour us, but proved like <hi>Graſs-hoppers</hi> eaſily diſperſed? And from the Gun-Powder Plot that threatned to contend by Fire? <hi>but this alſo ſhall not be, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And hath not he repeated theſe Warnings by the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> and <hi>Fire.</hi> that made a very great Deſtruction; but not a full end of us? Nay, hath he not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100231:10"/>trippled them by the <hi>horrid Iriſh Rebellion</hi> in 41, and the <hi>Civil Wars</hi> that threatned our Diſſolution? And alſo by our late Dangers that were like to have been more Fatal to us, if a Patient God had not ſeaſonably interpoſed to deliver and reſtore us to this happy State in which we have another opportunity to reform and repent, that we may eſcape the laſt Effects of his Deſtructive Vengeance? And if we don't improve it aright, we have cauſe to fear what may be the dreadful Iſſue of ſuch a Fatal Neglect.</p>
            <p>A 3d Cauſe of our Fear is, <hi>That very few are ſincere and hearty in the Work of Reformation begun among us:</hi> Alas! this is too evident to be doubted; for tho' ſome <hi>Zealous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of our</hi> Jeruſalem are active to promote it: yet they are but a ſmall number; and how many are very backward and unwilling to be engaged in it? nay, what vaſt Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes do ſtill reſiſt, and at beſt, are only <hi>Paſſive,</hi> and muſt be forced to comply with it; but do ſtill love their Sins, which they are compell'd to leave; and are ready to return to them again, if Reſtraints were removed. Your Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth ſadly prove this, ſo that I need not ſay any more of it, to convince ſuch as you are, of this reaſon of our fear.</p>
            <p>The 4th Cauſe of our Fear is, <hi>The want of National Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and publick Acknowledgements of the great iniquities that have abounded in theſe Kingdoms.</hi> We have had ſome days of Humiliation upon other Occaſions; but there hath not yet been ſo much as a general Confeſſion of the grievous Sins of the <hi>Two laſt Reigns.</hi> Whether we have been too tender of their Reputation or our own, it's certain we have not expoſed them openly, and humbled our ſelves for them, with grief and ſhame before the Lord; which is neceſſary to vindicate the Glory of God, and deliver us from a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Deſtruction: For tho' a patient God may ſpare the worſt of particular Sinners in this Life, becauſe he will repay them fully in that to come; yet Nations will not appear as ſuch to be judged and puniſhed in the next World; and therefore cannot eſcape the direful Effects of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100231:10"/>Divine Vengeance in this, without a publick Repentance for National Sins.</p>
            <p>A 5th Cauſe that increaſes our Fear, <hi>as it aggravates</hi> our Guilt and Danger is, what <hi>Judah</hi> is accuſed for, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.6, 8, 10. That when <hi>She had ſeen all that God had done to Back-ſliding</hi> Iſrael, <hi>yet her treacherous Siſter</hi> Judah <hi>feared not, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord but feignedly, and not with the whole Heart.</hi> And have we not as doleful Inſtances of the ſad Deſolations of other <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> whom the Lord hath made to drink very deep of the Cup of his Indignation? and may he not cauſe us to drink of the Dregs of it? A Jealous God is on his way, and begun to puniſh others, and ſhall we eſcape? What reaſon have we to fear the laſt and moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Effects of his Wrath, if we do not fear and turn to the Lord with our whole Heart?</p>
            <p>The 6th Cauſe of our Fear is, <hi>That we come ſo far ſhort of the Reformation in</hi> Joſiah<hi>'s days:</hi> And if he executed the fierceneſs of his Wrath upon them, notwithſtanding all their ſucceſsful Attempts to reform the Nation, what ſhall become of us, who have not extended the Reformation ſo far as they did, either as to the Places and Perſons that were reformed, or the Sins that were ſuppreſſed?</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>As to the Places and Perſons that were reformed.</hi> The Reformation in <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Reign was not confined to the City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Benjamin</hi> that were preſent in it; but extended to all the Cities of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin:</hi> Nay, their Zeal carried it to all the Countrys that pertained to the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to <hi>Bethel,</hi> and the Cities of <hi>Samaria,</hi> that were not directly ſubject to the Kings of <hi>Judah:</hi> But it may be, that after the Ten Tribes were carried Captives, ſome of <hi>Judah</hi> Tranſplanted themſelves, and made Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies there; which gave an advantage to the Zealous King of <hi>Judah</hi> to ſuppreſs their Idolatries, <hi>and cauſe them alſo to ſerve, even to ſerve the Lord.</hi> But alas! we have cauſe to lament it, that few other Cities do follow your Pious Example, and a very ſmall part of the <hi>Country</hi> is yet reformed. Our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100231:11"/>
               <hi>Plantations</hi> abroad are ſtill a Reproach to our Nation and Religion by their inſolent Wickedneſs and uncontrouled Impieties: And nothing is yet done to reclaim the <hi>Natives</hi> of this Kingdom from their Abominations: and, <hi>it may be,</hi> that for this Sin they have been ſo often the <hi>Rod</hi> of God's Anger to correct us; and if we ſtill neglect their Souls, they may become the <hi>Sword</hi> of his Vengeance to deſtroy us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We come as far ſhort of their Reformation, <hi>with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Sins that were ſuppreſt: for all the Abominations that were ſpied in the Land of</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>and that were in all the Countries of the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>did they put away,</hi> and reſtored their Religious Worſhip to its greateſt Purity, <hi>according to all the Law of</hi> Moſes: So that their Reformation ſeemed to be perfect in this Reſpect; but ours is very defective, for it hath not yet been extended ſo far. And many great Sins, which our Penal Laws do not reach, are ſtill committed with Impunity; and thoſe that are puniſhable do often eſcape: Some Perſons pretend to a Prerogative above the Laws of God and Man, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane the Sabbath. How much precious time is ſinfully miſpent in <hi>Ale-houſes</hi> and <hi>Taverns,</hi> thro' the Week! and ſome are not aſhamed to be found in them on the <hi>Lord's Day,</hi> if they are not catch'd there in the ſhort time of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service: Nay, what Curſing and Swearing, Perjury and Blaſphemy, Oppreſſion and Injuſtice, Lewdneſs and Prophaneneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſtill abounding among us? And many are impudent to ſerve the <hi>Devil</hi> by ſuch Wickedneſs, when few are Zealous for God, to give Information, and put the Laws in Execution againſt them: And if they did not eſcape that were ſo much more reformed;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer</hi> 5.29</note> what ſhall become of <hi>ſuch a ſinful Nation as this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 7th and laſt Cauſe of our Fear that I will mention, is <hi>from the many other Sins which abound among us,</hi> that cannot eaſily be reſtrained by Humane Laws, nor fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a Reformation. As many Back-ſlidings and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſions in the Ways of God; great Formality and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100231:11"/>in his Worſhip; Murmuring Complaints,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cer.</hi> 10.10.</note> and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content at the Providence of God; Diviſions and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among Profeſſors: The Sins of <hi>Sodom,</hi> as <hi>Pride,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49.</note> 
               <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Bread, and abundance of Idleneſs;</hi> Love of the World, and Covetouſneſs which is Idolatry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For theſe, and ſuch like Sins, may the Wrath of God be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out upon a People; and ſo much of them is found among us that may juſtly increaſe our Fears; that notwithſtanding all our Reformation, <hi>the Lord may not turn from the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Wrath, wherewith his Anger is kindled againſt us,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But ſome may poſſibly think,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Objection.</note> that theſe things are unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable upon this Occaſion and <hi>Object,</hi> that they expected only Encouragements to this Work: and behold! I have diſcouraged them altogether; for to what purpoſe ſhall they be active in it, if notwithſtanding all they do, we are ſtill in danger? and how can they be diligent that are poſſeſſed with theſe Fears?</p>
            <p>Anſwer 1.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>If there be ſuch real grounds of Fear, it's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſafe nor prudent to conceal, and be iguorant of them:</hi> for the Judgments we fear will neither come ſooner, nor be greater, becauſe they are foreſeen and diſcerned at a diſtance: Every wiſe Perſon will deſire to know his Danger:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.3.</note> 
               <hi>For the Prudent Man foreſeeth the Evil, and hideth himſelf, but the Simple paſs on, and are puniſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>True Zeal will not be diſcouraged, but rather animated by apprehenſions of Danger;</hi> as true Valour never appears ſo much as in the moſt hazardous Attempts. It's a puſillani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Spirit that ſhrinks at the appearance of Danger, and ſinks under its own Fears: Nay, ſuch Fears will rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the moſt active Endeavours; and ſhould make the Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diligent, and the Coward couragious. Perſons in a Storm need no other Motive to excite them to the uſe of all means for their Safety, than a Senſe of their Perilous Condition: their Danger is ſufficient to provoke their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence; and we never labour ſo hard and ſucceſsfully as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100231:12"/>when we <hi>work with Fear and Trembling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phillip.</hi> 2.12.</note> So that theſe are proper Motives to excite your Zeal, and quicken your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in this Work.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>'Tis not a Proſpect of the Event, but a Senſe of Duty, that doth chiefly determine Upright Perſons in their vertuous Attempts:</hi> for whatever be the Iſſue of them, 'tis their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be found Faithful in the way of Duty. And as it hath been ſufficiently proved to be your great Duty; ſo it may be a tryal of your Sincerity, if in the face, and over the fears of all Dangers, you are conſtant and vigorous in the Work of Reformation.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>If you are Sincere and Zealous in this Work, you ſhall not loſe your Reward;</hi> which doth not depend upon your Succeſs, but your faithful Diligence in it. And, ſuppoſing the worſt that your Fears can ſuggeſt, concerning the Iſſue of it; the Lord will accept your Labours, and make you Honourable; you may deliver your own Souls, have great peace,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4, 5.</note> and hopes of Everlaſting Glory. <hi>Your Work is with your God, and you ſhall be Glorious in his Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Tho' there be ſuch cauſes of Fear to make you ſerious, yet there are alſo grounds of Hope to encourage and make you cheerful in this Work.</hi> 'Tis a very critical Seaſon in which God keeps us upon our good Behaviour, that you may be cautious and careful to approve your ſelves to him in what you do; we have treſpaſſed againſt the Lord, and therefore ſhould be afraid of his Judgments.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Yet now there is hope in</hi> Iſrael <hi>concerning this thing: Now, therefore let us make a Covenant with our God, and put away all our Iniquities, and let it be done according to the Law: Ariſe, for this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter belongeth unto you; be of good Courage, and do it:</hi> For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Applicat.</hi>
               </note> In the next place I will ſhow you what are the grounds of our Hope concerning the iſſue of this Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and your generous Labours in it. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>You may lengthen out your Tranquility, procure a long Reprieve, and delay the Execution of threatned Judgments for a great while.</hi> You know not how far you may prevail
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100231:12"/>with a patient God, who hath often and long ſpared a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Nation, but never poured out his Wrath upon a reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People. We may hope to eſcape whilſt ſuch Zealous Reformers ſurvive:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 34.28.</note> and (as it was promiſed to <hi>Joſiah</hi>) <hi>You may be gathered to the Grave in Peace, that your Eyes may not ſee all the Evil that he will bring upon this Place, and upon the Inhabitants of it.</hi> And as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſaid in ſuch a caſe, 2 <hi>Kings,</hi> 20.19. <hi>Good is the Word of the Lord; and is it not good if Peace and Truth be in my days?</hi> So it's good and worth all your Labours, if you prolong Peace and Truth as long as you live; and they may be continued much longer. And in the mean time, how much good may be done? how many may be converted and Eternally ſaved? Some may be prepared for their ſhare of thoſe Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and become uſeful to ſupport and comfort others, and preſerve a ſenſe of Religion under them all. Nay, your faithful Diligence may have a further influence, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the violence, and ſhorten the continuance of thoſe miſeries, and procure an happy Iſſue out of them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore a more proſperous State after they are paſt. Such have been the bleſſed Effects of the like Attempts, and may be ſo again; for the God you ſerve is as Patient and Long-ſuffering, as Merciful and Gracious, as ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Your Zealous Endeavours may be Crowned with much greater Succeſs; and prevail ſo far as to remove all the Cauſes of our Fears, and ſupply all the defects of this Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> that it may become effectual at laſt, to avert the Judgments threatned againſt us altogether: For hath not the Work proſpered in your hands hitherto beyond all Mens Expectations? and who knows whereunto it may grow? and who would not take Encouragement to perſevere and encreaſe their Diligence, when they find by glad Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that their Labours are not in vain? It's very obſervable, what freſh Encouragement and great Advantages you have obtained upon every Occaſion of this nature:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.2.</note> For even ſince the laſt time you have found <hi>that the Lord is with you while
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100231:13"/>you are with him:</hi> For by your Zealous Diligence, and the large Bounty that was liberally contributed to this Work, you have been ſucceſsful in proſecuting thoſe Lottery Games that had the pretence of Authority to ſupport them. And what can ſtand before your vigorous Zeal? How much Leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Prophaneneſs hath been ſuppreſt in this City? And we are told of conſiderable Progreſs that is made in other places. Our King, like the great <hi>Joſiah,</hi> hath called the Elders toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and effectually recommended it to them in Parliament, and they have made good Laws to promote it: Some Judges do earneſtly recommend it to the Juſtices of Peace, and Magiſtrates in their Circuits, and greatly encourage the Execution of them. Some Perſons of conſiderable Intereſt both in Church and State in <hi>England,</hi> begin warmly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſe it, and (as we are told) they expreſs their Regret, that they have ſo long neglected it, and ſuffered meaner Perſons to get the Honour of it. You have the Almighty God on your ſide, whoſe Work you do; and who makes it to proſper:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> So that <hi>Mountains become Plains before you; and therefore let none deſpiſe the day of ſmall things; for he that laid the Foundations of this Work may alſo finiſh it, and bring forth the head Stone thereof with Shoutings; crying, Grace, Grace unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>A Spirit of ſerious Practical Religion is poured out upon many;</hi> and that which doth very much encourage our Hopes, that God hath ſome kind thoughts of Love and Peace for the riſing Generation, is, that plentiful meaſures of it are fallen upon many young Perſons; who are combined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ſeveral Societies for the Exerciſes of Godlineſs; and they are all continually praying for you: nay, you have the Prayers of all the Godly for your Succeſs.</p>
            <p>And is it not from the ſame Spirit of Peace and Love, that there is ſuch a bleſſed Harmony and Agreement among them of different Perſuaſions in other matters; who conſpire joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together to carry on this Excellent Work? And I hope, when ſome unreaſonable Jealouſies and Prejudices are worn
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100231:13"/>off, that it will procure a greater Union, which the envious endeavours of ſome ſpiteful Men ſhall not be able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. No ſmall meaſures of a Spirit of Zeal have alſo been poured forth upon ſome Magiſtrates and Inhabitants of this City, and the Work hath proſpered in their Hands; <hi>not by Might, nor by Power, but by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> And how neceſſary and effectual ſuch Divine Aſſiſtances are to perfect this Work hath been ſufficiently proved in a former diſcourſe of this nature;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Weld's</hi> Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> and our hopes are exceedingly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the ſucceſsful appearances of them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>The preſent Revolution of Providence we are fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, doth alſo encourage our Hopes:</hi> for if we underſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing of the Apocalyptick Writings, the Antichriſtian Kingdom is begun to fall, and will gradually decline to its total Diſſolution; and the Churches of Chriſt muſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably advance to their beſt, and moſt flouriſhing Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And tho' the Witneſſes may be ſlain, yet its only in <hi>one Street of the great City,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.8, 12.</note> and they ſhall ſoon riſe again to a better State. All Affairs in the World muſt effectually concur to the accompliſhment of theſe Predictions; and now the Wheels of his Chariots ſeem to move very ſwiftly, and make haſte, by the frequent great changes in the World, to perform ſome glorious Work that he hath deſigned for the great Happineſs of his People. And being well aſſured, that we have eſpouſed his Cauſe, and are a part of his true Church, we may comfortably expect, that he who hath done ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for us already, to deliver us from the very brink of Ruin, and reſtore us to all the Priviledges we enjoy, will perfect his Work, and bring to paſs the great deſigns of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences and your Endeavours, which appears to be the ſame.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>There is an amazing Providence of late that gives fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Encouragement to our great Hopes;</hi> which I will briefly mention, <hi>viz.</hi> That after all the Confuſions and Wars that have been in moſt Nations of the World, we are ſuddenly ſurprized with an Univerſal Peace.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 46.9.</note> 
               <hi>He hath made Wars to ceaſe to the ends of the Earth.</hi> And uſually ſuch a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100231:14"/>is accompanied with ſome great deliverance, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Church; as there have been many Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; particularly. The Reign of <hi>Solomon</hi> was the time of greateſt Peace and higheſt Advancement of the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament. In the Reign of <hi>Darius,</hi> when the Temple was rebuilt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.11.</note> and the Church moſt reformed, all <hi>the Earth was ſtill, and at reſt.</hi> In the days of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> when the Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> was ſhut,<note place="margin">The Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> was never to be ſhut, but when there was an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Peace thro' the World; and this was the third time of its ſhuting.</note> Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt came into the World, and laid the Foundations of the Goſpel Church. And <hi>Cnſtantine</hi> the Great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Peace to the Empire, and great Proſperity to the Church of God. And what may we now expect will be the Iſſue of ſuch a ſudden change of Affairs in the World? How quickly is the Scene altered, and the moſt hoſtile Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions agreed in a general Peace? Surely, he hath huſh't the World into this quiet condition, becauſe he is about to do ſome great thing for the good of his Church; and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming People ſhall have the largeſt ſhare of ſuch Bleſſings.</p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis no ſmall ground of our hopes in the laſt place, that a day of Solemn Humiliation hath been lately obſerved in moſt Proteſtant Churches abroad, and in our Neighbouring Lands; and is now appointed in this Kingdom by a publick Proclamation: <hi>That we may lay to Heart the Sins and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of our perſecuted Brethren, and deprecate the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which our manifold Sins and Provocations have moſt juſtly deſerved.</hi> And if we improve ſuch an happy Seaſon, only to <hi>acknowledge our Iniquities wherein we have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſt, and turn to the Lord with our whole Heart;</hi> we ſhall ſupply the two fatal defects of <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Reformation, and may eſcape ſuch Judgments as befel the Jews: who knows what ſuch a day may bring forth? Let every one act their part, and provoke one another in a publick Confeſſion of the notorious Sins we are ſtill guilty of; that by a <hi>National Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> Gods Wrath may be turned away, his Favour and the Bleſſings of it procured, our Fears prevented, and our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100231:14"/>Hopes take place. And this leads me to the laſt thing I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by way of Application; which is,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To give you ſome directions how to behave your ſelves,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Applic.</hi>
               </note> that if it be poſſible, we may be delivered from the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Evils our Sins have deſerved. And becauſe every Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this Nature hath abounded with them, I ſhall briefly mention only theſe few.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Have a due Regard unto God, whoſe Cauſe you have eſpouſed.</hi> Have a ſincere Reſpect to his Glory as your End, and his Word as your Rule. Pray earneſtly for his Counſel, Aſſiſtance, and Bleſſing; and be ſure to avouch him for your God, by making a Solemn Covenant with him: I mean not, a National one, which you cannot do without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Publick Authority, but a Perſonal one, to ſecure an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him thro' <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi> For what will it avail you, to reform others from their publick groſs Sins, if you periſh at laſt for your own ſecret Hypocriſie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.</note> 
               <hi>In this rejoyce not, that Spirits are ſubject to you, but rather rejoyce that your Names are written in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Guard againſt thoſe Sins you are moſt in danger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Direct. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and have been oft warned of; as Pride, Vain-Glory, private Revenge, Prejudices, Slaviſh Fears, Cowardly Withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Raſh and Irregular Attempts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Provoke others to give their Aſſiſtance to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Work you are engaged in.</hi> Recommend it by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to your Acquaintance in other places, and ſpeaking to thoſe you converſe with: Give them advice from your own Experience; and advance the Reputation of it by your Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Zealous Example. And if you have not acceſs to them, that may have Influence upon the Reformation of our <hi>Colonies</hi> abroad, or the Converſion of our <hi>Natives</hi> at home; yet do you conſult and contrive what may be the moſt proper methods to promote ſuch a neceſſary part of this Work. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and ſpeak of them as you have opportunity; it may be that your words will reach and ſtir up ſome that have Power, to make uſe of it for ſuch Glorious Ends.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100231:15"/>
            <p>And let this alſo have a ſhare in your fervent Prayers, that your <hi>Zealous Deſires</hi> may, if your Endeavours cannot, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to the utmoſt Bounds of ſuch a neceſſary Reformation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Where the Law is defective to ſuppreſs ſome Vices, by its Penal Sanction: <hi>Uſe the moſt Prudent Methods to reclaim thoſe you have any influence upon. Diſſwade</hi> them from their conſtant Tippling Clubs, and haunting the Ale-houſe and Tavern thro' the Week: from their vain Recreations, and walking abroad on the Lords Day: from their unlawful or exceſſive Gaming, and frequenting the Theatre, and vain Plays, and ſuch like ſcandalous Occaſions of Vice and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety. A prudent Admonition in your Name may prevail much with them, that have any Shame or Probity remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for God hath highly honoured your Societies, ſo that your Counſels may be as effectual as Commands; and your Reproofs as ſucceſsful as the Reſtraints of a Penal Law.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,<note place="margin">Direct. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let every one be diligent and ready, according to their Ability, to give all the aſſiſtance they can.</hi> You that are not choſen Members of theſe Honourable Societies, do not envy, but ſupport them; do not reproach, but vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them. Be ready to give Informations as you have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity; and to aſſiſt on Juries for the proſecution of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. Repeat and inlarge your Liberal Contributions as there ſhall be occaſion: and let us all be fervent in our Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to <hi>Almighty God,</hi> that he would bleſs the Zealous Endeavours of thoſe Renowned Inhabitants of our <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> that are <hi>doing according to the Covenant of God, the God of our Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100231:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
